In the previous video, we talked about the back propagation algorithm.
在上一段视频中 我们介绍了反向传播算法
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
To a lot of people
对很多人来说
seeing it for the first time,
当第一次看到这种算法时
the first impression is often
第一印象通常是
that wow, this is
哇哦
a very complicated algorithm and there are all
这个算法需要那么多繁杂的步骤
these different steps. And I'm
简直是太复杂了
not quite sure how they fit
实在不知道这些步骤
together and its like kind
到底应该如何合在一起使用
of a black box with all these complicated steps.
就好像一个黑箱 里面充满了复杂的步骤
In case that 's how you are
如果你对反向传播算法
feeling about back propagation, that's
也有这种感受的话
actually okay.
这其实是正常的
Back propagation may be unfortunately
相比于线性回归算法
is a less mathematically clean or
和逻辑回归算法而言
less mathematically simple algorithm
从数学的角度上讲
compared to linear regression or
反向传播算法
logistic regression, and I've
似乎并不简洁
actually used back propagation, you know, pretty
对于反向传播这种算法
successfully for many years and
其实我已经使用了很多年了
even today, I still don't sometimes
但即便如此
feel like I have a very
即使是现在 我也经常感觉
good sense of just what
自己对反向传播算法的理解并不是十分深入
it's doing most of intuition about
对于反向传播算法究竟是如何执行的
what background propagation is doing.
并没有一个很直观的理解
For those of you that are doing
做过编程练习的同学
the programming exercises that will
应该可以感受到
at least mechanically step you
这些练习或多或少能帮助你
through the different steps of
将这些复杂的步骤梳理了一遍
how to implement back prop
巩固了反向传播算法具体是如何实现的
so you will be able to get it to work for yourself.
这样你才能自己掌握这种算法
And what I want to do
在这段视频中
in this video is look a
我想更加深入地
little bit more at the
讨论一下
mechanical steps of back propagation
反向传播算法的这些复杂的步骤
and try to give you a little
并且希望给你一个
more intuition about what the
更加全面直观的感受
mechanical steps of back prop
理解这些步骤究竟是在做什么
is doing to hopefully convince you
也希望通过这段视频
that, you know, it is at least a reasonable algorithm.
你能理解 它至少还是一个合理的算法
In case even after this video, in
但可能你即使看了这段视频
case back propagation still seems
你还是觉得
very black box and kind
反向传播依然很复杂
of like, you know, too many complicated
依然像一个黑箱 太多复杂的步骤
steps, a little bit magical to to
依然感到有点神奇
you, that's actually okay.
这也是没关系的
And even though,
我说了
you know, I have used back prop
即使是我 接触反向传播这么多年了
for many years, sometimes it's a difficult algorithm to understand.
有时候仍然觉得这是一个难以理解的算法
But hopefully this video will help a little bit.
但还是希望这段视频能有些许帮助
In order to better understand back
为了更好地理解
propagation, let's take another
反向传播算法
closer look at what forward propagation is doing.
我们再来仔细研究一下前向传播的原理
Here's the neural network with two
幻灯片所示的神经网络
input units that is not
包含两个输入单元
counting the bias unit, and
这不包括偏差单元
two hidden units in this
在第二层有两个隐藏单元
layer and two hidden units
在下一层也有两个隐藏单元
in the next layer, and then
最后的输出层
finally one output unit.
有一个输出单元
And again, these counts 2,
再提醒一下 这里说的2 2 2
2, 2 are not counting these bias units on top.
都不算顶上附加的偏差单元+1
In order to illustrate forward
为了更清楚地展示前向传播
propagation, I'm going to
我想把这个网络
draw this network a little bit differently.
画得稍微不同一些
And in particular, I'm going to
具体来讲
draw this neural network with the
我把这个神经网络的节点
nodes drawn as these very
都画成椭圆型
fat ellipses, so that I can write text in them.
以便在节点里面写字
When performing forward propagation,
在进行前向传播时
we might have some particular example,
我们可以用一个具体的例子说明
say some example x(i) comma
假如说 训练样本
y(i) and it will
x(i) y(i)
be this x(i) that we
那么这里的 x(i)
feed into the input layer, so
将被传入输入层
that this may be,
因此这里就是
x(i)1 and x(i)2 are the
x(i)1 和 x(i)2
values we set the input
这是我们输入层的值
layer to and when we
那么
forward propagate it to the
当我们进行前向传播
first hidden layer here, what
传播到第一个隐藏层时
we do is compute z(2)1 and
我们的做法是 算出 z(2)1
z(2)2, so these are the
和 z(2)2
weighted sum of inputs of the
因此这两个值
input units and then
是输入单元的加权总和
we apply the sigmoid of
接下来
the logistic function and the
我们将S型的逻辑函数
sigmoid activation function applied
和S型的激励函数
to the z value, gives us
应用到z值上
these activation values.
得出了这样的激励值
So that gives us a(2)1
因此我们得到 a(2)1
and a(2)2, and then we
和 a(2)2 的值
forward propagate again to get,
然后 再做一次前向传播
you know, here z(3)1,
这里的 z(3)1
apply the sigmoid of the
应用S型的逻辑函数
logistic function, the activation function
和激励函数
to that, to get the
得到 a(3)1
31 and similarly Like so,
类似这样进行下去
until we get z(4)1, apply the
最后我们得到 z(4)1
activation function this gives
应用激励函数
us a(4)1 which is the
得到 a(4)1
finer output value of the network.
这也是这个网络的输出单元的值
Let's erase this arrow to
我把这个箭头擦掉
give myself some space, and if
这样留点书写空间
you look at what this
那么
computation really is doing, focusing
如果你仔细看这里的计算
on this hidden unit
关注这一层的隐藏单元
lets say we have that
我们知道了这个权值
this weight, shown in
这里用桃红色表示的
magenta there, is my
这是我们的权值
weight theta 2(1)0 the
θ(2)10
indexing is not important, and this
这里的角标不重要
way here which I guess
而这里的权值
I am highlighting in red, that
我用红色来标记的
is theta 2(1)1 and
是θ(2)11
this weight here, which I'm
而这里的权值
drawing in green, in a cyan,
我用青色表示的
is theta 2(1)2 so
是θ(2)12
the way the computers value z(3)1
因此要计算 z(3)1
is z(3)1 is as
z(3)1 的值等于
equal to this Weight,
这个桃红色的权值
times this value so that's
乘以这个值
theta 2(1)0 times 1,
也就是θ(2)10 乘上1
plus this red
加上这个红色的权值
weight times this value, so
乘以这个值
that's theta 2(1)1 times
也就是θ(2)11
a(2)1, and finally this
乘上a(2)1
cyan red times this value,
最后是青色的权值乘上这个值
which is therefore, plus theta
也就是
2(1)2 times a(2)1.
θ(2)12乘以a(2)1
And so that's forward propagation.
那么这就是前向传播
And it turns out that, as
事实上
we see later on in this
正如我们后面将会看到的
video, what back propagation
反向传播的做法
is doing, is doing a
其过程
process very similar to
非常类似于此
this, except that instead of
只有计算的方向不同而已
the computations flowing from the
与这里前向传播的方向从左至右
left to the right of this network,
不同的是
the computations is there flow
反向传播的算法中
from the right to the
计算的方向是
left of the network, and using
从右往左的
a very similar computation as this,
但计算的过程是完全类似的
and I'll say in two
在接下来的两页幻灯片中
slides exactly what I mean by that.
我会详细地讲解
To better understand what back
为了更好地理解
propagation is doing, let's look
反向传播算法的原理
at the cost function, it's just the
我们把目光转向代价函数
cost function that we had for
这个代价函数
when we have only one output unit.
对应的情况是只有一个输出单元
If we have more than
如果我们有不止一个
one output unit, we just
输出单元的话
have a summation, you know, over the
只需要对所有的输出单元
output units index, if only
进行一次求和运算
one output unit then this
但如果只有一个输出单元时
is a cost function operation and
代价函数就是这样
we do forward propagation and back propagation on one example at a time.
我们用同一个样本同时来做正向和反向传播
So, let's just focus on the
那么 请注意这组训练样本
single example x(i)y(i), and focus
x(i)  y(i)
on the case of having one output
注意这种只有一个输出单元的情况
unit so y(i) here
那么这里的 y(i)
is just a real number, and
就是一个实数
let's ignore regularization, so lambda
如果不考虑正则化
equals zero, and this final
也就是说 λ 等于0
term, that regularization term goes away.
因此最后的正则化项就没有了
Now, if you look inside
好的 那么如果你观察
this summation, you find that
这个求和运算括号里面
the cost term associated with
与第i个训练样本对应的
the I'f training example, that
代价项
is, the cost associated with training
也就是说
example x(i)y(i), that's
和训练样本 x(i) y(i) 对应的代价项
going to be given by this expression, that the
将由这个式子确定
cost, sort of, of training example
因此 第 i 个样本的代价值
i is written as follows.
可以写成如下的形式
And what this cost
而这个代价函数
function does, is it plays
所扮演的角色
a role similar to the square error.
可以看作是平方误差
So, rather than looking at this
因此 我们不必关心
complicated expression, if you
这个复杂的表达式
want you can think of cos
当然如果你愿意
of i being approximately, you know, the square of
你可以把 cost(i) 想成是
difference between or the
该神经网络输出值
neural network outputs versus what
与实际值的
is the actual value. Just as
差的平方
in logistic regression, we actually
就像在逻辑回归中
prefer to use this slightly
我们选择稍微复杂的一点的
more complicated cost function using
代价函数
the log, but for the
log函数
purpose of intuition, feel free
但为了容易理解
to think of the cost function
可以把这个代价函数
as being sort of the squared
看作是某种
error cost function, and so
平方误差函数
this cos of i measures how
因此 这里的cos(i)
well is the network doing on
表征了该神经网络
correctly predicting example i.
是否能准确地预测样本i的值
How close is the output
也就是输出值
to the actually observed label y(i).
和实际观测值y(i)的接近程度
Now let's look at what back propagation is doing.
现在我们来看反向传播是怎么做的
One useful intuition is that
一种直观的理解是
back propagation is computing these
反向传播算法就是在计算
delta superscript l
所有这些δ(i)j项
subscript j terms, and we
并且我们可以
can think of these as
把它们看作是
the quote error of the
这些激励值的
activation value that we
"误差"
got for unit j in
注意这些激励值是
the layer, in the
第 l 层中的
lth layer.
第 j 项
More formally, and this is
更正式一点的说法是
maybe only for those of
也许那些比较熟悉微积分的同学
you that are familiar with calculus,
更能理解
more formally, what the delta
更正式地说
terms actually are is this:
δ 项实际上是
they're the partial derivative with respect
关于 z(l)j 的
to z(l)j, that is
偏微分
the weighted sum of inputs that
也就是 cost 函数
we're computing the z terms,
关于我们计算出的 输入项的加权和
partial derivative respect of these things of the cost function.
也就是 z 项的 偏微分
So concretely the cost function
所以 实际上这个代价函数
is a function of the label
是一个关于标签 y
y and of the
和这个 h(x) 的值也就是
value, this h of
神经网络输出值
x output value neural network. And
的函数
if we could go inside the neural network
如果我们观察该网络内部的话
and just change those z(l)j
把这些 z(l)j 项
values a little bit, then
稍微改一点点
that would affect these values that the neural net.
那就将影响到该神经网络的输出
And so that will end up changing the cost function.
并且最终会改变代价函数的值
And again really this
当然 还是那句话
is only for those of you expert in calculus.
讲这些只是对那些熟悉微积分的同学
If you are familiar with comfortable with partial derivatives.
如果你对偏微分很熟悉的话
What these delta terms are,
你能理解这些δ项是什么
is they're, they turn out to
它们实际上是
be the partial derivative of the
代价函数
cos function with respect to these intermediate terms that we're computing.
关于这些中间项的偏微分
And so their measure of
因此 它们度量着
how much would we like to
我们对神经网络的权值
change the neural network's weights in
做多少的改变
order to affect these intermediate values
对中间的计算量
of the computation, so as
影响是多少
to affect the final output the
进一步地
neural network h of x and
对整个神经网络的输出 h(x) 影响多少
therefore affect the overall cost.
以及对整个的代价值影响多少
In case this last part of
可能刚才讲的
this partial derivative intuition, in case
偏微分的这种理解
that didn't make sense, don't worry
不太容易理解
about it, the rest of this
没关系
we can do without really
不用偏微分的思想
talking partial derivatives but let's
我们同样也可以理解
look in more detail at what
我们再深入一点
back propagation is doing.
研究一下反向传播的过程
For the output layer, if first
对于输出层
sets this delta term, we say
如果我们设置δ项
delta 4(1), as y(i)
比如说 δ(4)1 等于 y(i)
if we're doing forward propagation
假设我们进行第i个训练样本的
and back propagation on this
正向传播
training example i. It says it's y(i)
和反向传播
minus a(4)1,
那么应该等于 y(i) 减去 a(4)1
so it's really the error, it's
因此这实际是两者的偏差
the difference between the actual value
也就是 y 的实际值
of y minus what was
减去预测值
the value predicted.
得到的差值
And so we're going to compute delta
这样 我们就算出了
4(1) like so.
δ(4)1 的值
Next we're going to do propagate these values backwards.
接下来我们要对这些值进行反向传播
I explain this in a second
我稍后将详细解释
and end up computing the delta terms of the previous layer.
计算出前一层的 δ 项的值
We're going to end up
那么这里我们计算出
with delta 3(1); delta 3(2);
δ(3)1 和 δ(3)2
and then we're going to
然后同样的
propagate this further
再进行下一层的反向传播
backward and end up
这一次计算出
computing delta 2(1) and
δ(2)1
delta 2(2).
以及 δ(2)2
Now the back propagation calculation
反向传播的计算
is a lot like running the
和进行前向传播几乎相同
forward propagation algorithm, but doing it backwards.
唯一的区别就是方向相反
So here's what I mean.
我想表达的是
Let's look at how we end
我们来看我们是怎样得到
up with this value of Delta 2(2).
δ(2)2 的值的
So we have Delta
我们要计算 δ(2)2
2(2) and similar to
与前向传播类似
forward propagation, let me label a couple of the weights.
我要对一些权值进行标记
So this weight should be one cyan--let's say
那么这条权值 用桃红色表示的
that weight is theta 2
就是 θ(2)12
of 1, 2 and this
然后这根箭头表示的权值
weight down here, let me highlight
我用红色来标记
this in red. That's going to be, let's say,
它代表的是
theta 2 of 2, 2.
θ(2)22
So if we
所以
look at how Delta 2(2)
我们来看
is computed. How it's computed for this note. It turns
δ(2)2是如何得到的
out that what we're
实际上
going to do is
我们要做的是
we're going to take this value and
我们要用这个 δ 值
multiply it by this weight and
和权值相乘
add it to this value
然后加上
multiplied by that weight.
这个 δ 值乘以权值的结果
So it's really a weighted sum
也就是说 它其实是
of the new, these delta values.
这些δ值的加权和
weighted by the corresponding edge strength.
权值是这些对应边的强度
So concretely, let me fill this in.
让我把这些具体的值写出来
This delta 2,2 is going to
δ(2)2 的值
be equal to theta 2(1)2,
等于桃红色的这条权值
which is that magenta weight,
θ(2)12
times delta 3(1) plus, and
乘以δ(3)1
then the thing I have in red, that's
加上 下一个是用红色标记的权值
theta 2(2)2
θ(2)22
times Delta 3(2).
乘上δ(3)2
So it is really, literally this red
所以 简单地说
weight times this value, plus this
就是红色的权值乘以它指向的值
magenta weight times it's value
加上 桃红色的权值乘以它指向的值
and that's how we wind up with that value of delta.
这样我们就得到了上一层的 δ 值
And just as another example, let's look at this value.
再举一个例子
How did we get that value?
我们来看这个 δ 值
Well, it's a similar
是怎么得到的呢？
process, if this weight,
仍然是类似的过程
which I'm going to highlight in
如果这个权值
green, if this weight is
用绿色表示的这根箭头
equal to, say, delta
假如这个权值
3(1)2, then we have
是θ(3)12
that, delta 3(2) is
那么 δ(3)2
going to be equal to
将等于这条绿色的权值
that green weight, theta 3(1)2
θ(3)12
times delta 4(1).
乘以 δ(4)1
And by the
另外顺便提一下
way, so far I've been
目前为止
writing the delta values only
我写的 δ 值
for the hidden units and
仅仅是隐藏层中的
not, but not, excluding the bias units.
没有包括偏差单元+1
Depending on how you define
包不包括偏差单元取决于你
the back propagation algorithm or depending on
如何定义这个反向传播算法
how you implement it, you know,
或者取决于你怎样实现这个算法
you may end up implementing something
你也可以
to compute delta values for
对这些偏差单元
these bias units as well.
计算 δ 的值
The bias unit is always output
这些偏差单元
the values plus one and they
总是取为+1的值
are just what they are and there's
一直都这么取
no way for us to change
我们不能也没有必要
the value and so, depending
更改偏差单元的值
on your implementation of back prop,
所以还是取决于你实现反向传播的方法
the way I usually implement it,
通常说来 我在执行反向传播的时候
I do end up computing these
我是算出了
delta values, but we
这些偏差单元的δ值
just discard them and we
但我通常忽略掉它们
don't use them, because they don't
而不把它们代入计算
end up being part of
因为它们其实
the calculation needed to compute the derivatives.
并不是计算那些微分的必要部分
So, hopefully, that gives
好了 我希望这节课
you a little bit of intuition
能给你一个 有关反向传播算法的实现过程
about what back propagation is doing.
更深刻的印象
In case of all this, they
我知道可能这些过程
still seem so magical and
还是看起来很神奇
so black box, in a
很“黑箱”
later video, in the
不要紧 在后面的课程中
putting it together video, I'll try
在"putting it together"视频中
to give a little more intuition about what that back propagation is doing.
我还会再介绍一点有关反向传播的内容
But, unfortunately, this is, you
但是很遗憾的是
know, a difficult algorithm to
要想完全看清并且理解这个算法
try to visualize and understand what it is really doing.
的确是很困难的
But fortunately, you know,
但我想
often I guess, many people
幸运的是 多年来
have been using it very successfully
很多人都能顺利地运用
for many years and if
反向传播算法
you infer the algorithm, you have
并且如果你执行一遍整个算法
a very effective learning algorithm, even
你就能掌握这种很强大的机器学习算法
though the inner workings of exactly
尽管它内部的工作原理
how it works can be harder to visualize.
的确显得很难观察